{
  "reference_number": "9388",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I don’t think even the Nett Zero all gases is sufficient. If you look at the science we are already now well above a safe level of CO2 and\n other global warming gases and need to get back to a safe level of perhaps 350ppm CO2 in the atmosphere. So a nett negative\n target is the only scientifically justifiable option, I would like to see this as an option. Secondly I think we need to be able to comment\n\n on the rate of change to get to Zero Carbon in 2050 – eg it could all be left to the last minute or it could be via steep initial cuts –\n these two options would have significant differences in climate change effects yet both fit the zero carbon 2050 definition. I would go\n\n with the steep initial cuts in emissions to get the maximum climate benefits."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "This is essential after the fraudulent hot air emissions from other countries used up until recently. We mustn’t do this again and in fact\n we don’t have to - NZ is in a very fortunate position to be a world leader in having a low carbon economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes but only for a more stringent target. This is really important - there must be a ratchet mechanism where it can only be made a\n more ambitious goal."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I don’t trust future governments not to backslide over this under pressure from fossil fuel and animal farming industries, budgets\nneed to set in concrete. If we have an exceptional event, climate change isn't going to wait while we pollute some more, we just need\n\nto redouble our efforts to meet the necessary goals whatever comes our way. If we are determined we will find a way."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We need to abandon the idea that growth in GDP is a relevant metric for judging the health of our society. We need prosperity without\n\n(GDP) growth. The people who invented GDP (apparently) suggested it should never be used for judging the health of a society, yet\nthis is what we routinely do. We need to embrace the concept of enough. So rather than growth in GDP, we should ask whether the\n\nbudget we are setting will leave a good place for our grandchildren to live in. Rather than asking if we will be better off in 30 years, we\nneed to ask what state the planet will be in, what our rates of personal happiness will be rather than suggesting the more we\nconsume the happier we will be. We need to ask ourselves how what we are doing affects intergenerational equity. And we need to\n\nabandon the notion that business as usual for any industry is an option (if they are a high polluting one). I get really annoyed with the\nstatements of how much a zero carbon act will cost each household - the high polluting ones off course will pay a lot, but for us who\n\nhave very low carbon lifestyles, it will cost very little. There will of course be a huge range of costs - averaging it out is meaningless\nand is overly influenced by big polluters: If someone has to go tramping in NZ instead of trekking in Nepal due to the carbon costs of\n\nflying is that really a valid downside to the legislation? If someone has to reduce their meat consumption and move to a more plant\nbased diet is that actually a cost? If a family have to use an electric train rather than a private fossil fuelled car, is that really a cost? The\n\nreason the present ETS has been so supremely ineffective in moving us to a low carbon future is precisely the lack of resolve to have\nthe costs of carbon emissions be borne those responsible for those emissions. We can't muck around with this we need steep early\nemission costs so people get a strong early message to change their ways."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Optional comment I don’t trust future governments not to backslide over this under pressure from fossil fuel and animal farming\nindustries, so the ETS needs to be run at arms length from the government. Secondly the Climate Change Commission should set a\n\nfloor for the carbon price – eg it will never be less than $50/tonne. Any income surplus from carbon mitigating available at a lower\nprice should go into climate mitigation measures such as extending and electrifying the railway network. It is not at all clear to me why\n\nthe government should put a cap on the maximum carbon price. A floor yes, but a cap no. We want to make it crystal clear that high\nemissions will result in high costs, no ifs and buts and maybes. We need a swift transition to a low carbon economy, with no doubt\nthat there will be a significant carbon price for big polluters."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Mitigation, the stopping of climate change, will be where the real bunfight will be and this needs to be the clear focus of the Zero\nEmissions Bill. Adaption will be pretty obvious and insurance companies will help with this, making sea level rise vulnerable places\n\nimpossible to insure, forcing adaption measures. If we don’t mitigate well adaption will be so much worse. And perhaps most\nimportantly, if the Zero Emissions Bill is burdened down with carry adaption along with mitigation, it will become that much harder to\n\nget buy-in across the political spectrum."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "As above, the Zero Carbon Emissions bill needs to be clearly focused on the most important thing of mitigation. If we don’t get\nmitigation right, adaption will be radically worse. And perhaps more importantly if the Zero Emissions Bill is burdened down with\n\nhaving to carry adaption with it, it provides too much ammunition for people to shoot it down and prevent it coming into serious\naction."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "As above – a clear eyed focus on mitigation is required"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes, I would like to make some points about how we get to negative Nett emissions by 2050: It’s pretty obvious really, we need a\npretty much wholesale change from animal protein to plant based protein diets across the world and an all but complete shift from\nanimal agriculture to growing tree crops (avocados, other fruit, nuts), grains, ground nuts, pulses etc. Farmers don’t have to stop\n\nfarming, they just have to stop farming animals. There are so many other reasons for moving away from animal farming (surface water\npollution, aquafer pollution, poor production of protein per unit of land, per unit of water) that if we are going to feed the worlds 9\n\nbillion people we can’t afford to stay with such an inefficient means of production. And if we care about other living creatures what\nplace does eating them have? We need create carbon stores wherever possible. One is a “wood first” basis for all our buildings, so\n\nyou have to have a very peculiar reason to use steel or concrete columns and beams in commercial buildings as well as domestic. We\nneed to have an earth first approach to adding thermal mass in buildings (eg asking why can’t you use earth floors, earth walls etc in\n\nthis situation). Why are you not using carbon storing strawbale insulation rather than glass fibre batts (that have been produced at\n1000°C). Why are you not using timber windows and doors? This is not just to reduce emissions from steel, concrete, fibreglass\nmanufacture, but to have our commercial buildings as well as residential buildings acting as carbon stores. We need to have thermal\n\npower stations sited where the residual heat can be used to displace the coal burnt in greenhouses (like the Waimea plains here in\nNelson), that supplies heat and electricity just at the time that heat and power is needed (winter evenings when the grid is\n\nstruggling), but furthermore is designed to produce biochar to permanently lock up the carbon the trees have absorbed from the\natmosphere. And this biochar can be used as a soil enhancer as well as a permanent carbon store. And of course we need to\n\nreafforest most of the country, a lot of it with perpetual native carbon forests – certainly areas within 10m for every 1m of width of\nwatercourse. We need to move freight by the most efficient means of steel wheels on steel rails using electricity as the fuel, by\nextending and electrifying the rail network in the country (the argument of double handling costs is largely taken over by using curtain\n\nsider containers (perhaps using the additional advantage of containers of being able to be left in factories to be loaded at their\nleisure), taken by electric short range trucks, to the railhead, container moved directly from truck to rail wagon, taken by rail to\n\ndestination where container is transferred to electric truck and to destination – again perhaps left to be unloaded at the destinations\nleisure. Electric main trunk lines are of course a well established technology, but electric delivery trucks are already available too.\n\nSettlement patterns are a crucial and overlooked way of transitioning to a low carbon, necessarily energy efficient way of living. It is\nhard to see sprawling suburbia often covering productive soils, ever being able to be served well or efficiently by public or active\n\ntransport. Additionally it is a waste of resources with the extra length of trench, pipes, footpath, and roadway. We need to be free to\nbuild a second dwelling on our close in suburbs (building a second dwelling in far flung suburbs does nothing, that is not what I am\nasking for), make it easier to build up to our side boundaries 2 stories. The mantra needs to be, the next time you buy a new house\n\n(and I believe we do this every 7 years on average) buy closer to where you work, school or recreate. Electric Bikes, Cycles, buses in\nbus lanes, trams and trains on their separate networks need to be acknowledged as the only way of dealing with road congestion:\n\nwidespread commuting by electric cars, however worthy a replacement for fossil cars in terms of climate change, are still just as much\na disaster for urban form, livable cities and urban life. So whilst of course there needs to be a savage feebate for motor vehicles\n\ncoming into the country, with high emitting vehicles of any type paying a lot in feebates, while the most efficient in terms of CO2\nemissions getting a big grant towards their purchase price from the feebate scheme, we mustn’t kid ourselves that electric cars will\n\ndo anything to improve the inefficient land use car commuting demands. With roads and car parking taking up at least a half of our\ncities walkability is destroyed, liveable cities are impossible. Sewerage Schemes and Landfills should be designed to be first and\n\nforemost methane producers to generate a supply of non fossil gas. Certain gas uses like cooking with gas are not so easy to\nsubstitute out with electricity. Renewable methane availability will be a good substitute."
    }
  ]
}
